After Daddy died, Kaoru and Tomoki were separated.
（薫）＜パパが死んで　薫と友樹は 離れ離れになりました＞
But Daddy's friend Marumo
＜でも　パパのお友達のマルモが→
said we could live with him.
一緒に暮らそうって 言ってくれました＞
I'm thinking about living with these kids.
（護）この子たちと 一緒に暮らそうと思うんです。
Along with a dog called Mook.
＜ムックという犬も一緒です＞
-Can you talk? -Of course I can.
（薫）しゃべれるの？ （ムック）当たり前だろ。
We made an Okite* Notebook (*rules/code)
＜３人で 仲良く暮らしていくために→
so that the three of us can live together happily.
おきてノートを作りました＞
Kaoru and Tomoki will soon be first graders.
＜薫と友樹は もうすぐ１年生になります＞
First time I've had to do two loads of laundry.
洗濯機　２回も回したの 初めてだよ。→
Finally done.
やっと終わったわ。
He looks dirty too.
（護）あいつも汚れてんな。→
Hey. Hey.
おい　おい。 んっ？
I'll let the dog stay, but he's gotta get washed.
（護）犬も置いてやる代わりに 洗濯だ。
Bring him here.
こっち連れてこ～い。 は～い。
No, no, no, I don't wanna be washed.
やだ　やだ　やだ　洗濯やだ。 んんっ　ん～。
You're going to be living with us so
一緒に住むんだもん→
you have to get clean.
ちゃんと奇麗にしないと駄目。 よいしょ。
I can't take it anymore.
（ムック）う～　もう限界。
I'm hearing things again.
この辺ですか？ また聞こえた　俺。
Mook! Get him, get him, get him.
ムック！ 捕まえろ　捕まえろ　捕まえろ。
Hurry, hurry, hurry. Stop!
早く　早く　早く。 あっ　待て～！
Look what you've done.
おっ　何やってんだよ　これ。
I was almost finished too.
もうちょっとだったのに もう　これ。　やだ。
You guys...this..
あっ？　お前ら　ちょっと　これ→
You drew on the poster I made, I didn't you?
俺が　せっかく作ったポスター 落書きしたろ。
-I drew the flowers. Aren't they cute? -That's too much.。
お花　描いたの　カワイイでしょ？ 描き過ぎだよ　お前。
They shouldn't stand out more than the dog.
犬の写真より目立っちゃ駄目。
And this... this must be Tomoki, huh?
あと　これ　これは友樹だろ？
What's this...this picture of seaweed.
何なんだ　この　モズクの絵は。
-That's Mook. -I give up.  What a mess.
それ　ムック。 やだ。　もう　むちゃくちゃだよ。
Oh, dang. It's time.
あっ　ヤベえ　もう時間だよ。
Hey guys, we're going out. Hurry up and get ready.
おっ　お前ら　出掛けるぞ。 おい　ちゃっちゃと用意しろ。
Hurry up, hurry up.
（薫・友樹）は～い。 早く　早く。
The (school) entrance ceremony will be held on April 6th.
校庭　広い。 （杉下）入学式は４月６日です。→
From the following day, they will only have classes in the morning for a while,
翌日から　しばらくは 午前中のみの授業で→
and they will come to school in groups.
集団登校になります。→
The meeting places are noted in this handbook, so
集合場所は　この　しおりに 書いてありますんで→
please make sure you verify your location.
確認しといてください。
Yes, I'll do that.
はい　了解しました。
Um...Excuse me for asking,
（杉下）あの 大変　失礼なんですけど→
but these children aren't your real children, are they?
子供たち２人は 実のお子さんではないんですよね。
No, they're my friend's children.
そうですね　友人の子供です。
You're not the guardian either.
後見人にもなられてませんよね。
The children's uncle is their guardian.
後見人は子供たちのおじさんです。
I'm just taking care of them. Is that a problem?
僕は預かってるだけなんですけど 何か問題でも？
No, no. Technically, there's no problem, but
いや　いや　いや 手続き上　問題はありませんが→
will you be alright? There's quite a few school supplies and such that will be needed.
大丈夫ですか？ 入学準備とか結構ありますけど。
You're right.  There's quite a few.
あはっ　結構ありますね。
Oh, and these are the various expenses,
あっ　それから　こちらが→
like lunch fees, that you'll have to bear.
給食費など お願いする費用になります。
These are for one child, so
これは１人の場合で→
for two children, you'll have to double up everything.
２人ですと　掛かる手間も　お金も ２倍になりますけど。
Double?
２倍？　ハハ　ハハハハ…。
Supplies to be provided?
準備していただく物？
Apron, ...rags for cleaning, bag for indoor shoes.
え～　エプロン うわ～　雑巾　上履き袋。
Wow, we got our work cut out, huh?
うわっ　これ大変だな　おい。 あっ？
I will now take roll. Sasakura Tomoki-san.
では出席をとります。 笹倉　友樹さん。
-Here. -Trade places.
はい。 （友樹・薫）交代。
I will now take roll. Sasakura Kaoru-san.
では出席をとります。 笹倉　薫さん。
Here.
はい。 （薫・友樹の笑い声）
-Are you guys looking forward to school? -Yeah. I can't wait to be in first grade.
お前ら　学校　楽しみか。 うん　早く１年生になりたい。
Me too.
僕もなりたい。
Do you guys know what you do at school?
お前らさ 学校　何するとこか知ってっか？
It's not a place you go to play, it's a play you go to study, you know.
遊ぶとこじゃねえぞ 勉強するとこだぞ。
-I want to study. -Sasakura Kaoru-san,
薫　お勉強したい。 おっ　笹倉　薫さん→
-don't forget that spirit. -Yes.
その気持ちを忘れずに。 はい。
I want to eat the school lunch.
僕　給食　食べたい。
And I want to play with my friends, and then I want to eat the school lunch.
それに　お友達と遊んで あとは　給食　食べたい。
Sasakura Tomoki-san, you eat too much school lunch. -Yes.
笹倉　友樹さん　給食　食い過ぎ。 はい。
It's exciting, isn't it?
楽しみだな。
Oh, and I wanna go look for ransel* too (*leather backpacks used by Japanese grade schoolers)
あっ　あと　僕 ランドセルしてみたい。
A black and definitely cool one.
黒いやつで　絶対カッコイイやつ。
That's right. We have to buy ransel too.
そっか　そうだよな ランドセル買わなきゃな。
Will we have just enough time?
ぎりぎり大丈夫か？
-Let's go buy it now. -Yay.
今から行くか。 やった。
Alright. Ransel.  A black one.
よし。 ランドセル　黒いやつ。
-Ransel. Black one. -Ransel...
（友樹・薫）ランドセル…。
45,000 yen? (approx. $558)
４万５，０００円？
Times 2 is 90,000 yen?
を２個で　９万円？
This is our most popular model.
（店員）こちらは 一番　人気のタイプになりますね。
-Would you like it? -Um...give me 5 seconds...
いかがなさいますか？ あの　ちょっと　５秒　下さい。
I'll take them.  Red and black, one of each.
買います。　赤と黒　１個ずつ。
-With this card.  In installments. -Thank you very much.
カードで。　分割。 かしこまりました。
Yay, I got a black one.
やった　黒いやつ。
-Kaoru, what's wrong? -Nothing.
薫　どうした？ ううん　何でもない。
We have other colors too.
（店員）あっ ほかにも　お色ありますけど。
-Maybe you'd like a different color? -Kaoru, do you want a different color?
違う色がいいかな。 あっ　薫　ほかの色がいいか？
I want a pink...
わたし　ピンクの…。
Oh, I'm sorry.
（店員）あっ 申し訳ございません。→
Pink is a very popular color, and it's currently out of stock.
ピンクは人気のお色でして ただ今　在庫を切らしております。
Red's okay then.
じゃ　赤でいい。
I'm sorry. So will red be alright?
ごめんね。 では　赤で　よろしいですか？
Kaoru, let's look for a pink one then. Okay?
薫　だったらピンク探すか。　なっ。
-Can we? -Sure. I'll look for it.
いいの？ おう　俺が探しといてやる。
Okay, thanks, Marumo.
うん　ありがとう　マルモ。 [TEL]（バイブレーターの音）
Oh, excuse me for a moment.
あっ　ちょっと　すいません。
Hello?
もしもし？
What are you doing, Takagi-san?
[TEL]（真島）何やってんですか 高木さん。
Oh, I'm shopping for ransel.
いや　今　ランドセル選んでた あっ。
-Ransel? -No, no, I mean...
[TEL]ランドセル？ いや　いや　いや→
I have the morning off today.
今日ね　半休もらってんだよ。
We have a big problem.
[TEL]大変です　トラブル発生ですよ。
What?
えっ？
It's this. The Strawberry Glue that went on sale last month.
（真島）これです 先月発売の　いちごのり。→
The stationery glue made to look like strawberry jam.
いちごジャム風の文具のりです。
Oh, the one that's been selling well. What's the problem?
ああ　結構　売れたやつ。 何が問題なんだ。
There's been a rash of children who mistakenly licked it.
（真島）間違って　なめちゃう子供が続出。
The phone's been ringing off the hook with complaints.
苦情の電話が 朝から殺到してるんです。→
Look, it even has seeds, and there's this scent.
ほら　種の粒々まで再現してるし このにおいでしょ。
-You can't blame them for making a mistake. -They got us here.
そりゃ勘違いしますよ。 これは追求しちゃったね。
-It certainly makes you want to lick it. -I've had it with
確かに　なめたくなるわ。 （凛花）もう　やだ。→
these complaints about getting sick from eating the whole jar.
全部　食べちゃって おなか壊したとか→
-I bet they're lying. -But why are we getting these complaints all of a sudden?
絶対　嘘ですよ。 でも　何で　いまさら　一斉に。
Someone wrote about it on a mother's blog.
ママさんブログに 誰かが書いたんですよ。
So people jumped on the bandwagon and are making false claims.
それに便乗して言い掛かりか。
Even so, we're still responsible.
（民子）だとしても こっちの責任よ。
We didn't have a cautionary note on it saying that it should not be consumed.
食べられる物ではありませんって 注意書き　入れてないんだもの。
We didn't?
入れなかったんすか？
We should've just stuck to our standard merchandise.
定番商品だけ 出してればいいものを→
It was out of character for us to try to sell fancy supplies.
急にファンシー文具だなんて うちの柄じゃなかったのよ。
I still think it's cute.
（凛花）うん でもカワイイんですけどね。
Yeah, I thought it was a great idea.
うん　このアイデア すごいと思ったけどな。
Samejima-san and the managers from PR and Sales
（真島）今　鮫島さんと 広報と営業の上の人が→
-are going around apologizing to the customers. -Wow, that's a tough job.
取引先に謝罪に出てます。 うわっ　大変だ。
Hello, Customer Service.
はい　お客様相談室　うっ。
Oh, the strawberry glue. We're very sorry.
あっ　いちごのり。 大変　申し訳ございません。
Tada~.
ジャーン。
Wow, cool.
（彩）お～　カッコイイ。
Looks good on you. That's nice.
お～　似合う　似合う。　いいね。→
What about you, Kaoru-can? Where's your ransel?
薫ちゃんは？ ランドセル　どうしたの。
I don't have mine yet.
薫のは　また今度。
The store didn't have the one I wanted so Marumo's going to look for it.
薫が欲しいの　お店になかったからマルモが探してくれるの。
Is that right?  How exciting.
（彩）そっか。　じゃ　お楽しみだね。
Oh, let me see.
（彩）あっ　見して。
What should I do?
どうしよう　これ。
-Here. -Thanks.
（陽介）はい。 あっ　すいません。
Are you still taking care of the kids?
（陽介）子供たち まだ預かってんの。
Oh, I decided to take them in.
あっ うちで引き取ることにしたんです。
-Take them in? -Yes.
（陽介）引き取るの？ はい。
What, what, what.
いや　いや　いや　何　何　何。
You mean you're going to be like a foster parent?
何　それって 親代わりになるってこと？
That sounds exaggerated, but I guess that's what it means.
そう言うと大げさですけど まあ　そういうことです。
That's not exaggerated.
（陽介）大げさじゃねえよ。
To take in other people's kids means
他人の子供を 引き取るっていうのは→
that you need to be determined and responsible, even more than real parents.
お前　実の親以上に 覚悟とか責任とかが必要だろ。
I realize that, of course.
いや　それは　もちろん。
You're not gonna get away with it
あっ 半端な気持ちで親代わりなんて→
if you think you can do it half-heartedly, you know.
許されねえんだよ。
I know.
分かってますって。
Can you really do it?
大丈夫か　お前。
Hey, your food's here.
おい　ご飯　来たぞ。 （薫・友樹）は～い。
My specialty, Kuji Rice.
おじさん特製のクジライス。
Oh boy, the kani-san sausage is on top too. Cute.
あっ　カニさんウインナーも 載ってる。　カワイイ。
Looks good. Itadakimasu.
うまそう。 いただきます。
-Itadakimasu. -Okay, eat up.
はい　召し上がれ。
-Is it good? -It's good.
おいしい？ （薫・友樹）おいしい。
I'm glad.
（彩）お～　よかった。
Why don't you come for lunch tomorrow too?
あっ　じゃあさ あしたのお昼も食べに来たら？
I'll make something cute with a sausage for you again.
またウインナーで カワイイの作ってあげるからさ。
-Yay.
やった。
You come down if anything happens too, okay?
（彩）ご飯以外でも　何かあったら すぐに下りてきなね。
No, that would be imposing on you too much.
（薫・友樹）は～い。 いや　それは悪いですよ。
Besides, I have readymade stuff for their lunch.
お昼は　ちゃんと 買い置きしてありますから。
Readymade stuff won't do. Children have to be
買い置きなんて駄目です。 子供には→
fed properly. You have to buckle down
しっかり食べさせないと。 親代わりなら→
-if you're going to be a foster parent. -I'm sorry.
ちゃんとしてください。 すいません。
-What's this? -Oh this...
何ですか？　これ。 あっ　これね→
It's a list of supplies they need for school.
入学までに　これだけの物を 準備しなきゃいけないんですよ。
Bag, lunch bag, apron, cleaning rags, bag for indoor shoes ...
（彩）んっ？　手提げバッグ　給食袋 エプロン　雑巾　上履き袋って→
-That's a lot of work to make all these. -What? I have to make them?
これ　全部　作るの　大変ですね。 えっ？　作るの？
Of course. Everyone makes them.
当たり前じゃないですか。 みんな作ってますよ。
Don't make it sound so simple.
そんな 簡単に言わないでくださいよ。
I haven't sewn anything since life science class
裁縫なんてね 小学校の家庭科の授業以来→
in grade school. That would be impossible.
やってないですから 無理に決まってるでしょ。
I want Marumo to make mine.
僕　マルモに作ってほしい。
Sasakura Tomoki-san, don't talk when you eating.
笹倉　友樹さん　食事中は静かに。
Yes.
はい。
Impossible. Absolutely impossible. Impossible.
無理。　絶対　無理です。　無理　無理。
It's too soon for you to get cold feet.
おじけづくの早過ぎです。
Aya, Aya.
（陽介）彩　彩。 （彩）んっ？
Why don't you help him out.
（陽介）お前さ　手伝ってやれよ。
-With what? -You know, you were saying
えっ　何を？ （陽介）いや　今　言ってたろ。
that lunch bags and stuff are handmade.
給食の袋とか 色々　手作りするって。
Why me?
何で　わたしなのよ。
Because you have the time.
お前　暇だろ。
So this was Hatanaka-san's storage room.
ここって 畑中さんとこの物置だったんだ。
He didn't tell you?
（彩）あっ　聞いてないんですか？
Pops just told me not to open the door, so
親父さんからは　開けるなとしか 言われてないんで→
at first I was scared that maybe he was hiding a corpse or something.
最初は死体でも隠してないかと ドキドキしたもんです。
Why would he do something like that.
そんなわけないじゃないですか。
I'm sure Mom's old sewing machine was in here somewhere.
確か　お母さんが使ってたミシンがあるはずなんだけど。
I'm sorry for troubling you.
何だか　すいません。
Huh? Where did it go?
あれ？　ないな。
It is here?
あっ　ここかな。
Oh, here it is.
あった　ありました。
I wonder if it still works.
動くかな　これ。
You place the fabric here.
（彩）で　布をここにセットして。 はい。
-And bring this to the back. -Back?
で　これを奥に。 奥？
Bring it down. That's right.
下ろしてください。　そう。
And you adjust the speed by stepping on the pedal,
で　足のペダルを踏んで スピードを調整するんですけど→
as you guide the fabric with your hand. -Guide it.
布に手を添えて。 添えて。
Ah...H-h-how.
あっ…　どっ　どっ　どうやって。
Hey, how do you s-s-stop...
ちょっと　どうやって とま　とま　とま…。
Help!
助けて！
Lots of kani-san sausages were attacking me
カニさんウインナーが いっぱい攻めてきて→
and I couldn't eat all of them.
僕　食べきれなかった。
What kind of dream is he having...
何て夢　見てん…。 （ムックの鳴き声）
It's a little noisy at night, so let's just sew by hand.
夜中は　うるさいから 手縫いにしましょうか。
Sew by hand?
手縫い？ （彩）うん。
-That's it. Put the needle through one more time. -Yes.
（彩）そう。　で　もう１回　刺して。 はい。
Yes, that's it.
うん　そうそう。
Finished. Finally.
できたよ。　やっと　できた。
Huh? Huh?
んっ？　んっ？　やだ。　やだ。
I give up.
もう　やだ。
We're very sorry for the inconvenience we caused you.
ホントに　ご迷惑　お掛けしました。申し訳ありませんでした。
Be careful from now on, will you?
（客）気を付けてくださいよ。 ホントに　もう。
They come complaining to us. Really getting tired of it.
うちにまで苦情が来るんだもん 勘弁してほしいよ。
For the time being, take these back.
取りあえず　これは引き取ってね。
Yes, we're sorry.
はい　申し訳ありません。
Stationery supplies are nothing to sneeze at.
文房具代もバカになんねえかんな。
Gotta cut my expenses where I can.
ちょっとでも節約しねえとな。
Takagi-san, what are you doing?
（かな）高木さん 何してるんですか？
Makimura-san. I was just...
牧村さん　いや　ちょっと。
You're thinking about taking some supplies for your personal use, aren't you?
（かな）あはっ　自分用に備品 使おうとしてるでしょ。
No, no, no. Of course, I'll pay for them.
いえ　いえ　いえ ちゃんと購入しますよ。
If I cheat like that, it would be considered corporate embezzlement.
そんな　いんちきしたら 業務上横領ですからね。
People who do that should be fired.  Fired.
そんなやつは　もう　首ですよ　首。
Wow, you're pretty hard-core.
（かな）お～　厳しいですね。
What are you doing here, Makimura-san?
牧村さんは　どうしたんすか？
Oh, my pen's out of ink.
あっ　ボールペンのインクが 切れちゃったんで→
I'm embezzling. And cheating.  Don't tell, okay?
横領です。　いんちき。　内緒ですよ。
My pen's out of ink. I'm embezzling.
インクが切れちゃったんで 横領です。
And cheating.
いんちき。　もう。
Here's the pattern for apron.
（彩）これがエプロンの型紙です。
Oh, apron.  Thanks.
ああ　エプロン。　どうも。
Also, go ahead and use these fabrics.
それと　これからは この布を使ってください。
-I'll give them to you. -They're cute.
あげます。 カワイイ。
-Aren't they? -Where did you get them?
（彩）でしょ。 どうしたの　これ。
I just happened to find some cute fabrics, so I bought them.
（彩）カワイイ布　見つけたんで 買っといたんです。→
Oh, they're cheap ones so don't worry about it.
あっ　安いやつなんで 気にせず　どうぞ。
Thanks a lot.
どうも　すいません。
Oh, that's right. I have some school supplies for you guys.
あっ　そうだ。　お前らに 学校で使う文房具　持ってきたぞ。
-Let me see.
見せて。
Tada~.
ジャーン。
Pencils, eraser, notebook.
鉛筆　消しゴム　ノート。
What's this. They're not cute at all.
何これ　全然かわいくない。
-Huh? -There's a lot of cute ones out there.
えっ？ もっとカワイイのあるでしょ。
You know, the ones with characters and glittery and colorful ones.
キャラものとか　こう きらきらでカラフルな感じとか。
But these are fine for me. They're fine for you too, right, Tomoki?
でも　薫　これでいい。 友樹もいいよね。
-I want the one with Ultraman. -These look more
僕　ウルトラマンのやつがいい。 これの方が→
-grown up and cooler. -No.
大人みたいでカッコイイじゃん。 やだ。
Yeah, these are better.
そうだよな。 これの方がいいじゃん。
Oh, look at this. Tada~.
あっ　そうだ。　ほら　これ。 ジャーン。
That's cute.
カワイイ。
Stationery glue ala strawberry jam. It's called just that too - strawberry glue.
いちごジャム風　文具のり。 その名も　まんまで　いちごのり。
-It looks so good. -But you can't eat it.
おいしそう。 食べちゃ駄目なんだってば。
We're having major problems because of that.
今　それで えらい問題になってんだから。
This is stationery glue, so you use it to do things like paste paper, crafts,
これはな　文具のりだから 紙をはったり　工作に使ったり。
-spread it on bread. Right, spread this all over
パンに塗ったり。 そうそう　こんがりトーストに→
lightly toasted bread, and bite into it... Hey, that's not it.
これをべたっと塗って　ぱくって 駄目　こら。
You're not supposed to do that.
しちゃいけないの そういうことは。
You're not supposed to put it on bread.
パンに塗ったりしちゃ駄目。 へえ→
So you guys sell this kind of things too.
でも　こんなのもあるんですね。
Yes, but this is the only thing geared for children.
はあ でも　子供用なんて　これだけです。
Oh speaking of,
ふ～ん。　あっ　そういえば→
have you found Kaoru-chan's ransel yet?
薫ちゃんのランドセルは 見つかったんですか？→
The entrance ceremony's coming up soon, isn't it?
もう入学式でしょ？ うん。
I'm still looking for one, so don't worry. Okay?
あっ　今　探してるから。 心配すんな。　なっ。
Okay, it's bedtime for the munchkins.
よし　じゃ　ちびどもは　もう寝ろ。
If you don't go to bed early, you're not gonna get to be in first grade.
んっ？ 早く寝ないと１年生になれねえぞ。
Aren't you going to bed, Marumo?
えっ？　マルモは寝ないの？
Not yet.
あっ　俺はいいんだよ。
You're not gonna get to be in first grade.
１年生になれないよ。
You just worry about yourself.
お前は自分の心配しろ。 （一同の笑い声）
Should I sleep for a while?
いったん寝ようかな。
Yeah, it'll be more efficient if I take a quick nap
うん　ちょっと寝て また起きて　やった方が→
and work on it some more after I wake up.
効率がいいと思う。
Yeah, let me sleep for a bit. Just for a little while.
うん　ちょっと寝よう ちょっとだけ寝よう。
I'm just going to lay down.
ちょっと横になって　うん。
But you're gonna end up sleeping all night, aren't you?
で　結局　朝まで寝ちゃうんだろ？
Yeah, soundly until morning.
うん　朝まで　ぐっすりだ。
I heard it again.
また聞こえた。
[In your case, you may be hearing
（桜子）《高木さんの場合 自分の心の中が→
what you're feeling in your heart.]
聞こえているのかも しれません》→
[Your subconscious feeling is taking the form of a voice.]
《無意識の思いが声となって》
Yes, you're absolutely right. Actually, I know that too.
そう　そのとおり。 ホントは自分でも分かってんだよ。
I always do this and end up sleeping until the next morning.
結局　朝まで寝ちゃうんだ そうやって　いつもな。
Alright, I'm gonna try to go on a little bit longer.
よし　もうちょっと頑張ろう。
Did you make that yourself?
（真島）それ 自分で　にぎったんですか？
Huh? Yeah, I'm trying to cut down on my expenses.
あっ？ あっ　そうだよ　節約中だよ。
-That's really sad. -Leave me alone.
（真島）わびしいな　もう。 大きな　お世話だよ。
Hello.
≪（かな）お疲れさまです。
Hello. Why are you here, Makimura-san?
お疲れさまです。　あれ 牧村さん　どうしたんですか？
-Is it ready? -Yes, this is it.
（鮫島）できた？ （かな）はい　これで　お願いします。
To deal with the issue with the strawberry glue,
えっ？ （かな）例の　いちごのりの件で→
we made a poster and stickers with a warning note.
注意書きのポスターと それからシール作ったんです。
Does this mean you want us to go around
（真島）もしかして 残ってる店舗　全部　回って→
the stores putting this sticker on?
商品に はってこいってことですか？
Yes, please.
はい　お願いします。
Wait, give me a break!
ちょっと　もう 勘弁してくださいよ。
The past several days we've been going around apologizing
ここ数日　店舗　回って　謝罪して→
and the phone calls have finally settled down too.
電話だって やっと落ち着いてきたとこなのに。
It's okay. I said we'd do it.
いいんだよ うちで引き受けたんだ。
-But Samejima-san... -What are we going to do with the inventory
えっ　ちょっと鮫島さん。 （鮫島）これ以上　返品されて→
if more stock is returned.
在庫が増えちゃ困るだろ。→
It's the right course of action for the company.
会社としても当然の判断だよ。
But is that our job?
（真島）でも それって　うちの仕事ですかね。
If the warning note is there, the customers are less likely to misunderstand,
注意書きがあれば お客さまの勘違いも減って→
and as a result, we'll get fewer complaints and claims.
結果的に苦情もクレームも 減ることになる。→
Even if it's a lot of work now, our department will benefit from it too.
今　面倒な思いをしても うちの部としても損はないだろ。
Thank you. We'd appreciate it if you could get it done this week.
すいません。　あの　今週中に何とかよろしくお願いします。
I'll go.  I'm going.
行きます。　俺　行ってきます。
-Huh? What? -Mashima, let's go.
（真島）はっ？　えっ？ 真島　行くぞ。
What? Huh? Wait, Takagi-san.
（真島）えっ　ちょっと　えっ？ ちょっと高木さん。
Let's go.
行くぞ。
-We're counting on you. -Yes!
頼むよ。 はい！
Oyaji-san, you're cruel.
（陽介）よし。 親父さん　ひどい。
Good bye, Mr. Fish.
お魚さん　さようなら。
That's why when we eat, we put our hands together
だから　食べるときには ちゃんと手を合わせて→
and say itadakimasu.
いただきますってやるんだ。
It means you're going to eat with gratitude.
ありがたく　いただきますっていう意味だからな。
Mr. Fish, itadakimasu.
お魚さん　いただきます。
It's too early yet.
まだ早いぞ。
-Tomo-kun, do you want to go for a walk? -Let's go, let's go.
（彩）友君　お散歩　行こっか。 行く行く。
-Where's Kaoru-chan? -Come to think of it,
（彩）あれ？　薫ちゃんは？ （陽介）ああ　そういや→
she hasn't come back since she went upstairs a while ago.
さっき　上　上がったきり 下りてこねえな。
Let me see.  We have language class tomorrow, so I'm studying Japanese.
え～と　あしたは国語があるから 国語の勉強しよっと。
I have to be able to write hiragana properly.
平仮名　ちゃんと書けないとね。
A-I-U-E-O
あいうえお。
-What are you doing? -Nothing.
何してんの？ ううん　何でもない。
How far shall we go?
（彩）どこまで　お散歩　行こっか。
I want to go to the school.
薫　小学校がいい。
-Me too. -Alright, the school it is.
僕も。 （彩）小学校か　そうね→
Okay, let's try to remember the way to school then.
じゃ　一緒に通学路を覚えよう。 （３人）おう。
"When I become a first grader, when I become a first grader"
（３人）♪♪「一年生になったら 一年生になったら」→
"Will I make 100 friends?"
♪♪「ともだち１００人　できるかな」
I used to walk by this shopping area
（彩）お姉ちゃんもね この商店街を通って→
to attend the same school as you guys, you know.
みんなと　おんなじ小学校に 通ってたんだよ。
The same one? Wow.
同じなの？　すごい。
Brings back memories. This area hasn't changed at all.
懐かしい。 この辺　全然　変わってないな。→
[Daddy, when are you going to get better?]
《ねえ　パパ パパは　いつ元気になるの？》
[Real soon. Why, I'll be all better before you know it.]
（笹倉）《そんなの　すぐだよ。 すぐに元気になる》
[Will you be better by the time I'm start first grade?]
《薫が１年生になるまでには なる？》
[Yes, I'll definitely be better by then.]
（笹倉）《うん　きっと　なるよ》→
[When I get better, let's go buy ransel together, okay?]
《元気になったら　一緒に ランドセル買いに行こうな》
[Okay. There's a ransel that I want.]
《うん 薫ね　欲しいランドセルあるんだ》
[It's pink, and it has lots of hearts on it.]
《ピンクで　ハートのマークが いっぱい付いたやつ》
[It's really cute. That's the ransel I want.]
《カワイイんだ。 絶対に　あのランドセル》
[I definitely want a cool one.]
《僕のは　カッコイイやつ　絶対》
[Okay, got it.  It's a promise.]
（笹倉）《うん　分かった　約束な》
[Pinky promise then.]
《うん　じゃ　指切り》 （笹倉）《んっ》
What's wrong?
≪（彩）どうしたの？
Nothing.
ううん　何でもない。
What a cute ransel.
（彩）へえ カワイイ　ランドセルだね。
It has a lot of hearts.
うん ハートが　いっぱい付いてるの。
I hope Marumo-san buys it for you.
マルモさん 買ってくれるといいね。
You sure threw me off, acting cool all of a sudden, Takagi-san.
（真島）急にカッコつけんだもん 高木さん。
-I wasn't doing that. -That's a lie. You got motivated
そうじゃねえよ　別に。 （真島）嘘だ　牧村さんに頼まれて→
as soon as Makimura-san asked you.
急に　やる気　出してんだもん。
There's a hungry kid who actually wanted to put this on toast, you know.
実際これをパンに塗ろうとした 食いしん坊がいるんだぞ。
It needs a warning note.
注意書きは必要だろ。
Besides, it's an item that's selling well. Right?
それに　せっかく売れてる 商品なんだから。　なっ。
By the way, how many more stores do we have?
ちなみにさ　あと何件　回んだっけ。
Three more.
あと３件です。
That many still, huh?
まだまだあんな。
Mashima, I'm going to the restroom.
真島 俺　ちょっと　トイレ行ってくるわ。
Takagi-san, the restroom's the other way.
（真島）高木さん　トイレ　逆です。
Oh, really?
あっ　そう？
Ah, found it.
あっ　見つけた。
It's pink, and half-price too.
ピンク　しかも半額。
I want this.  I want this no matter what
欲しい。　これ　絶対　欲しい。
Takagi-san. What are you doing?
（真島）高木さん 何やってるんですか？
What? Mashima.
えっ？　真島。
Why do you need a ransel?
ランドセルなんて 何に使うんですか？
I don't need it. I was just looking at it.
何にも使わないよ。　見てただけ。
But you were saying "I want it no matter what" just now.
いや　でも　今　「絶対　欲しい」って。
That's because, um, this...
それは　あれだ　え～と　これ→
Oh, use it for a shopping bag?
あっ　これ ショッピングバッグとして？
Look.  See, the opening is wide, right?
ほら　見て　これ ほら　これ　間口が広いでしょ？
So you can put milk and shoyu and all kinds of things in it.
だから　牛乳も入っちゃうし しょうゆも　どんどん入っちゃう。
Yeah, it's real practical. Plus, see?
うん　使いやすいんだ。 しかも　これ　ねっ→
It frees up your hands, so it's very convenient.
両手が空くから　ほら　便利。
It's sturdy and fashionable. Like in Daikanyama*... (fashionable district in Tokyo)
丈夫で　おしゃれ。 ねっ　今　代官山　行ってみな。
Everyone in Daikanyama's riding their bicycle
代官山　行ったら みんな　これ　しょって→
with this on their back. The reason being, it frees up their hands.
自転車　乗ってるよ。 なぜなら両手が空いてるから。
-See, you can wave your hand too. -I've never seen anything
ほら　ねっ　手も振れる。 いや　見たことないですよ→
-like that. -You've got to look around.  Pay more attention.
そんなの。 見なきゃ　もっと街を見なきゃ。
Let's do lunch sometime, with this on our back.
今度　ランチしよう これ　しょって　ねっ。
-Okay, I'm buying this. -What?
よし　俺　これ買っちゃう。 えっ？
Why does it fit so well. This is just great.
何で　こんな　なじむんだろ。 すごいわ　いいわ→
I finally met you. Where were you until now.
やっと出合えたわ。 どこにいた　今まで。
-Thanks. -Thank you.
（客）ごちそうさま。 （陽介）ありがとうございました。
Thank you.
（彩）ありがとうございました。
-You know. -What?
わたしさ。 （陽介）んっ？
Did I ever have reservations about asking you for something when I was a child?
子供のころから　お父さんに 遠慮なんかしたことあったかな。
Nope. Although there were times
ないね。 まあ　遠慮してほしいなって→
I wished you had reservations.
思ったことは たくさんあるけどな。
Right?
だよね。
Why are you asking all of a sudden? Are you finally feeling bad about it?
何だよ。　急に　どうした？ 今ごろ反省してんのか。
What are you saying. I'm talking about Kaoru-chan.
何　言ってんの。 薫ちゃんの話だよ。
She's really careful about holding back her feelings from Takagi-san.
あの子 高木さんに　すごく気を使ってて。
Well, that can't be helped.
（陽介）まあ そりゃ　しょうがねえだろ。→
It hasn't been too long since they started living together.
まだ一緒に暮らし始めて 日が浅いんだから。
But I feel a little bad for her.
でも　ちょっと　かわいそうでさ。
Don't go sticking your nose in other people's business, you hear?
お前な あんまり余計な口出しすんなよ？
He has to learn to deal with the kids himself.
子供たちとのことは あいつ自身の問題なんだから。
Takagi-san, let's get started. Oh, you already started.
（彩）高木さん　始めますよ。 あっ？　もう始めてる。
I'm in a panic mode. I only have until the day after tomorrow.
いや　さすがに焦ってますよ あさってまでだもん。
That's admirable.
（彩）ふ～ん　偉いですね。
Oh, how cute. You finally got your ransel.
あっ　ランドセル。 カワイイ　買ってもらったんだ。
Look.
うん　ほら。
[It has a lot of hearts.]
《ハートが　いっぱい付いてるの》
[I hope Marumo-san buys it for you.]
（彩）《マルモさん 買ってくれるといいね》
-Thank you, Marumo. -Yeah.
マルモ　ありがとう。 おう。
I'm really looking forward to the entrance ceremony. Marumo, you have to come too, okay?
入学式　楽しみだな。 マルモも来てね。
Yeah.
おう。
Seriously, what the heck is Takagi-san doing?
（真島）ったく 何してんだよ　高木さん。→
He won't even pick up his cell phone.
何回　電話しても　出ねえし。
Is this it?
ここか？
"We found a lost dog."
「迷い犬　あずかっています」
What's that guy doing?
≪（戸の開く音） （真島）何やってんだ　あの人。
Excuse me, did you want something?
（彩）あの　何か　ご用ですか？
Oh, um...
（真島）あっ　あの→
Takagi Mamoru-san lives up there, doesn't he?
高木　護さんのお宅って この上ですよね。
Yes.  Open that door there...
あっ　はい　そこの扉を開けると…。
I'm Takagi-san's colleague, Mashima Takanori.
あの　僕　高木さんの同僚の 真島　孝則っていいます。→
Nice to meet you.
よろしくお願いします。
Ah yes...Nice to meet you.
あっ　はい　よろしくお願いします。
Cute.
カワイイ。
Takagi-san, are you sleeping? Wake up. I'm here to get you.
（真島）高木さん　寝てます？ 起きてください　迎えに来ました。
Takagi-san, we have to visit five stores today.
高木さん　今日中に５店舗も こなさなきゃいけないんですよ。
This is Takagi-san's house, isn't it?
あれ？　あれ　ここって 高木さんのうちだよね。
Yes.
はい。
Who are you?
君　誰？
-Who are you, Oji-san? -Oji-san...
おじさんこそ誰ですか？ おじさん。
Oji-san is...I mean.. I'm actually Onii-san...
いや　おじさんは　あっ　いや まあ　お兄さんなんだけど→
My name is Mashima.
真島っていいます。
Shima-shima? -What? Not Shima-shima.
シマシマ？ えっ？　シマシマじゃなくて→
Mashima...Wait. Hey.
真島…　ちょっと。　あっ　ちょっと。
But what's a little girl doing here.
えっ つうか何で女の子がいんだよ。
Don't tell me he has a secret child?
えっ？　隠し子？　まさか。
Marumo. Shima-shima's here.
ねえ　マルモ。 ねえ　シマシマが来たよ。
Huh? Shima-shima?
んっ？　シマシマ？
Shima-uma (zebra)? -Shiro-kuma (polar bear)?
シマウマ？ シロクマ？
What the heck is that.
何だ　それ。
Mashima.
あっ　あっ　あ～　あ～　いや あっ　あっ　あっ　あっ　真島。
So you took them in? Both kids?
（真島）で　引き取ったんですか？ 子供　２人とも。
Yeah.
うん。
No wonder you were acting weird lately.
（真島）どうりで　最近 様子が変だと思ってたんですよ。
Yeah. I'm a fool, huh?
まあな。　バカだよな　俺。
I'd say.
（真島）そうですね。
Where else would you find such a soft-hearted guy.
（真島）そんな　お人よし ほかにいませんよ。
I'm home.
ただいま。
Sasakura Kaoru.
ささくら　かおる。
...kura Tomoki.
…くら　ともきだ。
...kura Kaoru.
…くら　かおる。
Sasakura Tomoru.
ささくら　ともる。
Not Tomoru. That won't do.
あっ　ともる。 駄目だ　ともるじゃ駄目。
Okay.
よし。
Alright, I made it.
よっしゃ　間に合った。
What~.
（薫・友樹）え～。
Marumo, you can't come to the entrance ceremony?
どうして　マルモは 入学式　来れないの？
I have lots of work again today. So I can't come to the entrance ceremony.
今日も　仕事　大変なんだよ。 だから入学式には行けない。
Come with us, Marumo. If you don't, you're not gonna get to be in first grade.
マルモも一緒に来てよ。 来ないと１年生になれないよ。
You guys being in first grade is good enough.
１年生は お前らだけで十分なんだよ。
But.
でも。
Kaoru, you're the big sister, so you'll be alright, won't you?
薫は　お姉さんだから 大丈夫だよな。
I'll be alright.
うん　大丈夫。
Then you take of Tomoki for me, okay?
うん　じゃ　友樹のこと頼んだぞ。
-Okay. -Alright, go on then.
分かった。 よし　行ってこい。
We're going.
いってきます。
Have fun.
いってらっしゃ～い。
Don't you have to go?
≪（ムック）行かなくていいのか？
It's the entrance ceremony, isn't it?
入学式だろ？
I don't have time for that right now.
行ってる場合じゃねえんだよ。
I don't have a choice.
仕方ねえんだ。　うん。
We're done with the stickers. Again, we apologize.
シール　はり終わりました。 申し訳ありませんでした。
-We're sorry. -Please be more careful.
（真島）申し訳ありませんでした。 （店員）気を付けてくださいね。
Where to next? The Home Center.
次　どこだっけ。 あ～　ホームセンターです。
-I bet they have a lot. -It might take a while.
数ありそうだな。 時間かかりそうです。
Can we just come in without permission?
（彩）ねえ　勝手に入っていいの？
They don't have enough space right now.
（陽介）いや　だって 今のままじゃ狭いだろ。→
And there's gonna be three of them from now on.
これから３人で暮らすんだし。→
Oh, you're home by yourself? Good boy.
あらら　１人で　お留守番か。 偉い偉い。
Mook? What do you have there?
（彩）ムック？　んっ？ 何くわえてんの？　これ。　んっ？
What? Bag for indoor shoes?
（陽介）どうした。 （彩）上履き入れ？→
They should have taken their indoor shoes today...
あれ？　今日は上履き 持ってってるはずなのに。
He must have forgotten them.
あいつ　忘れてってんじゃないか？
Excuse me.
ちょっと悪い。
Oh, sure.
あっ　はい。
-Hello. -Takagi-san?
はい。 [TEL]（彩）高木さん？→
Today's the kids' entrance ceremony, isn't it?
今日って２人の入学式ですよね。
-Yes. -Did you forget their indoor shoes?
そうですけど。 [TEL]あの　上履き　忘れてません？
Indoor shoes? I'm not sure.
上履き？　どうだったろ。
What do you mean you're not sure. Where are you now?
どうだったろって　えっ？ 今　どこにいるんですか？
Aren't you at the school?
学校じゃないんですか？
I'm at work.
[TEL]今　仕事中です。
Work?
仕事中？
This is the entrance ceremony, you know? Why didn't you go?
入学式ですよ？ 何で行ってあげないんですか。
There's been some trouble at work,
いや　今　仕事が大変なんですよ。
so at a time like this
そんなときに　俺だけ→
how can I say "Let me attend the entrance ceremony"?
「入学式　行かせてください」なんて言えないでしょ。
Everyone else is working.
[TEL]みんな働いてるんだから。
I can't believe it.
信じられない。
Children's entrance ceremony takes precedence for normal people.
普通 子供の入学式を優先するでしょ。
Those poor kids.
かわいそうですよ。
Don't act like you know it all when you don't know anything.
いや　何にも知らないくせに 勝手なこと言わないでください。
Tomoki was a little disappointed, but Kaoru understood.
友樹は少し残念がってたけど　薫はちゃんと分かってくれました。
You're the one who doesn't know anything, Takagi-san.
[TEL]何も知らないのは 高木さんの方です。
What?
えっ？
Kaoru-chan's desperately trying to hold it in.
薫ちゃん 一生懸命　我慢してるんです。
I'm the one who was desperately trying to get everything ready for them.
いや　こっちが　こんなに頑張って 準備してんのに→
What does Kaoru have to hold in?
薫は 何を我慢してるっていうんですか。
Things like desks and cute stationery...
勉強机だって カワイイ文房具だって→
The things every child wants.
子供だったら欲しいはずです。
And the ransel too.
それにランドセルも。
I did buy her one. The pink one that she wanted.
それだったら買ってやったでしょ ちゃんとピンクの探して。
What she really wanted was the ransel with the hearts.
ホントは　ハートのマークが入ったランドセルが欲しかったんですよ。
Hearts?
ハートのマーク？
I can't buy
そんな　欲しがったら→
everything the children wants.
何でも買ってやるってわけには いかないでしょ。
Besides, she never told me anything about hearts on the ransel.
それにランドセルのマークなんて 詳しく聞いてなかったし。
She couldn't tell you because she didn't want to impose on you.
[TEL]遠慮して 言えなかったんだと思います。
Huh?
えっ。
Children normally won't hesitate to say it
[TEL]子供だったら 普通　言いますよ。→
If even they know they won't get it, to be able to say
買ってもらえなくても 「買ってほしい」って→
"I want it" - that's what kids do, right?
そう言えるのが 子供じゃないですか。
But she held it in and couldn't tell you.
それなのに　じっと我慢して 言えなかったんです。
[I want the pink...]
《わたし　ピンクの…》
[What's wrong?]
《どうした？》
[Nothing.]
《ううん　何でもない》
[-Thanks, Marumo -Yeah.]
《マルモ　ありがとう》 《おう》
[I'm really looking forward to the entrance ceremony.]
《入学式　楽しみだな》
[They're not cute at all. There's a lot of cute ones out there.]
（彩）《全然かわいくない。 もっとカワイイのあるでしょ》→
[You know, the ones with characters and glittery and colorful ones.]
《キャラものとか　こう きらきらでカラフルな感じとか》
[But these are fine for me. They're fine for you too, right, Tomoki?]
《でも　薫　これでいい。 友樹もいいよね》
[Kaoru, you're the big sister, so you'll be alright, won't you?]
《薫は　お姉さんだから 大丈夫だよな》
[-Okay. -Alright, go on then.]
《分かった》 《よし　行ってこい》
Both of them
（彩）《２人とも→
were practicing their answer over and over
名前を呼ばれるときの お返事の練習→
for when their name was called.
何回もしてたんですよ》
[-Sasakura Tomoki-san. -Here.]
《笹倉　友樹さん》 《はい》
[-Sasakura Kaoru-san.
《笹倉　薫さん》
[-Sasakura Tomoki-san. -Here.]
《笹倉　友樹さん》 《はい》
[-Sasakura Kaoru-san.
《笹倉　薫さん》
[Hey, how many times are you going to practice?]
《ちょっと　２人とも 何回　練習する気なの？》
[As many times as we can. We're gonna answer real loud
《何回も。　ちゃんと マルモに聞こえるように→
so that Marumo can hear us.]
大きな声で　お返事するんだもん》
[-Sasakura Kaoru-san. -Here.]
《笹倉　薫さん》 《はい》
Takagi-san, is something the matter?
高木さん　どうしたんですか？
Today's the kids' entrance ceremony.
今日さ　あの子たち　入学式なんだ。
Yeah, it is.
そうなんだよ。
I swore to myself that I'd watch over them
俺　笹倉の代わりに　ちゃんと ２人のこと見守ってやるって→
in Sasakura's place.
そう決めたのに。
But I wasn't watching them.
見てなかった。
I wasn't watching over them like I should have been.
俺　あの子たちのこと ちゃんと見てやれてなかった。
Can't you still make it?
まだ　間に合うんじゃないですか？
Sorry.
すまん。
We will now call out the names of the new students.
それでは　新入生呼名。
When your name is called,
名前を呼ばれた人は→
please stand up and answer loud and clear.
大きな声で返事をして 立ってください。
-Asakawa Daichi-san. -Here.
（杉下）アサカワ　ダイチさん。 （アサカワ）はい。
-Andou Yuria-san.
（杉下）アンドウ　ユリアさん。 （アンドウ）はい。
-Ishii Itsuki-san. -Here.
（杉下）イシイ　イツキさん。 （イシイ）はい。
-Ishikawa Tsubasa-san.
（杉下）イシカワ　ツバサさん。 （イシカワ）はい。
-Itou Arisa-san. -Here.
（杉下）イトウ　アリサさん。 （イトウ）はい。
-Endou Manami-san.
（杉下）エンドウ　マナミさん。 （エンドウ）はい。
-Kawaguchi Kenta-san. -Here.
（杉下）カワグチ　ケンタさん。 （カワグチ）はい。
-Kubodera Kei-san.
（杉下）クボデラ　ケイさん。 （クボデラ）はい。
-Tezuka Minami-san. -Here.
（杉下）テヅカ　ミナミさん。 （テヅカ）はい。
-Look, Marumo's here. -No way.
ねえ　マルモ来てる　マルモ。 えっ　嘘。
-Koizumi Taiga-san. -Here.
（杉下）コイズミ　タイガさん。 （コイズミ）はい。
-Kogure Aoi.
（杉下）コグレ　アオイさん。 （コグレ）はい。
-Saitou Subaru-san. -Here.
（杉下）サイトウ　スバルさん。 （サイトウ）はい。
-Sasakura Kaoru-san.
（杉下）笹倉　薫さん。 はい。
-Sasakura Tomoki-san. -He~re.
（杉下）笹倉　友樹さん。 はひ。
-Shiina Mio-san. -Here.
（杉下）シイナ　ミオさん。 （シイナ）はい。
-Taniguchi Hayato-san.
（杉下）タニグチ　ハヤトさん。 （タニグチ）はい。
-Togami Genki-san. -Here.
（杉下）トガミ　ゲンキさん。 （トガミ）はい。
-Nakamoto Yuzuki-san.
（杉下）ナカモト　ユズキさん。 （ナカモト）はい。
-Hirose Hibiki-san. -Here.
（杉下）ヒロセ　ヒビキさん。 （ヒロセ）はい。
-Machida Haruka-san.
（杉下）マチダ　ハルカさん。 （マチダ）はい。
The 24 new students of Hirokawa Elementary of 2011.
（杉下）以上　広川小学校 平成２３年度　新入生２４名。
Marumo! Marumo.
≪（薫・友樹）マルモ！ マルモ。
Marumo, Marumo.
マルモ　マルモ。
Marumo, you came. Thank you.
マルモ　来てくれたの？ ありがとう。
Um..Sorry.  Anyway, sorry. For saying I couldn't come.
あの　ごめん。　何か　ごめん。 行けないとか言って。
We didn't think you were coming.
来てくれないと思ってた。
The bag that Marumo made for me,
マルモが作ってくれたバッグね→
my friend said it's cute.
お友達が カワイイって褒めてくれたよ。
-This bag too. -Is that right?
この袋も。 そうか。
I answered loudly too.
それと　元気に　お返事できたよ。
You know, Tomoki's cracked. He said "He~re."
友樹はね　声が裏返ったの。 「はひ」って。
-I got nervous. -Were you watching, Marumo?
緊張しちゃった。 マルモ　見てた？
I was watching.  I watched very carefully.
見てたよ　ちゃんと見てた。
Okay, let's get going.
よし　行くか。 （友樹・薫）うん。
Hey, shall we take a picture too?
おいおい　俺たちも　写真　撮るか。 （薫・友樹）うん。
Excuse me. Excuse me, but
あの　すいません。 すいません　あの→
-can I ask you to take our picture? -Sure.
写真　撮ってもらっていいですか？（保護者）あっ　いいですよ。
Thanks. It's all set up to go.
すいません 押すだけになってますから。
-Oh, Mook's here. -Mook.
あっ　ムックだ。 ムック。
What? Why is he here?
えっ？　何で　こいつ来てんだ？
You're taking a picture, aren't you? Don't forget about me.
写真　撮るんだろ。　僕を忘れんな。
-What? Did he talk? -Are you ready?
えっ？　しゃべった？ （保護者）いいですか？
Did you perhaps cry?
あれ？　もしや泣いた？
No, I didn't. What? Again.
泣いてねえよ。　えっ？　また。
-Excuse me, are you ready? -Yes, please.
（保護者）あの　いいですか？ あっ　はい　どうぞ。
Sit.
お座り。
Here we go.
じゃ　撮りま～す。
"We're in first grade now"
（薫・友樹）♪♪「一年生に なっちゃった」→
-"We have 100 friends now" -You guys lie.
♪♪「ともだち１００人　できちゃった」 嘘つけ。
Be careful now.
（陽介）無理するな。→
Your head. See, what did I just say.
頭　頭。　ほら　言っただろ。 （彩）もう。
-You're home. -Hi, welcome home.
あっ　おかえり。 （彩）あっ　おかえり。
-Hi.
ただいま。 （薫・友樹）ただいま。
Huh?
あれ？
What's this.
何だ　これ。
-It's a desk. -Wow!
机だ。 すごい！
That's my hand-me-down, but it's a present to celebrate your admission to school.
（彩）それ　わたしのお下がり。 入学祝いだよ。
-Alright! -Thank you.
やった。 （友樹・薫）ありがとう。
I'm not using this storage room anyway,
（陽介）この物置もさ どうせ使ってないんだ→
-so do what you want with it. -You really mean it?
好きに使ってくれ。 えっ　いいんですか？
Thank you very much.
すいません ありがとうございます。
-Let's sit down. -Let's study.
座ろう。 お勉強。
Look, a pencil sharpener. Yeah.
あっ　鉛筆削りだ。 ホントだ。
-Everyone, gather around. -What?
≪おい　みんな集合。 んっ？　何？
It's a new okite.
うん　新しい　おきてだ。
Oh, you can't read it, can you.
あっ　そうか　分かんねえか。
Enryo* is...? (*to hold back)
えんりょは？
Enryo wa muyou* (unnecessary)
うん　遠慮は無用。
-What's that? -We're a family, so
何それ。 俺たちは家族なんだから→
we should say whatever's on our mind.
お互いに言いたいことは言う。
If there's something you want, say so. It means it's okay to do that.
欲しいものは欲しいって言う。 それでいいってこと。
Okay, Kaoru?
なっ　薫。 うん。
-Okay, Marumo, I want ice cream. -You just had one.
じゃ　マルモ　僕　アイス食べたい。 さっき食っただろ。
But I want another one. Didn't you say enryo wa muryou?
でも食べたい。 えんりょは　むりょうでしょ。
It's muyou, not muryou*. (*free)
無料じゃなくて無用です。
That doesn't mean you're going to get everything you ask for.
何でもかんでも 聞いてやるってことじゃないの。
Ice cream's gonna attack you. What are you going to do?
アイスが攻めてくるぞ ぶわ～って。　どうする。
-Good morning. -Morning.
おはよう。 おっ　おはよう。
Oh, it's a heart.
あっ　ハートのマークだ。
Well, I couldn't buy you the ransel with hearts, but
いや　ハートのランドセルは 買ってやれなかったけど→
that's a heart too, right?
それもハートだろ？
That's so tacky~.
だっせ～。
What?
えっ？
It's cute.  Thanks, Marumo.
カワイイ。　マルモ　ありがとう。 おう。
Oh, it's an onigiri.  It looks yummy.
あっ　おにぎりだ　おいしそう。 ハハ。
No, I tell you, it's tacky.
いや　ださいって。
-Why? It's cute. -It looks yummy
何で？　カワイイじゃん。 おいしそうじゃん。
No, no, it's definitely tacky.
いやいや　ださいでしょ。
-I say it's cute. -I say it's yummy.
カワイイって。 おいしいって。
I say it's tacky.
ださいって。
You're kidding me? Did he just talk?
嘘でしょ？　今　しゃべってた？
-Were you talking with the dog? -What?
犬と　しゃべった？ 何が？
I mean, the dog's voice is really the voice of my heart,
いや　あの　犬の声っていうのは 俺の心の声でだな→
and he's actually not really talking, and...
ホントは　しゃべんないんだ ていうか　だす→
What? Why? What? Why are you talking?
えっ　どうして えっ　なっ　何で　しゃべってんの？
-He talks.
しゃべるよ。
-I talk. -What~? Why?
え～？　何で？